unding。
多謝主席。
會 payable in the event of a favourable outcome.
和提供相關措施和 safeguards。
委員會指出，根據《2008年税收條例》第98G條第2款。
議案獲得通過。二零一六年仲裁修訂條例草案。
In my capacity as the chairman of the Bills Committee on Arbitration and Mediation Legislation.
The case will therefore be fully or partly funded out of the working capital of the lawyer's firm.
Third Party Funding Amendment Bill 2016. I report on the deliberations of the Bill's committee.
of the arbitration ordinance to mediation, to which the mediation ordinance applies. The deliberations of the Bills Committee are summarised in the ensuing paragraphs.
本會恢復《二零一六年仲裁及調解法例第三者資助修訂條例草案》嘅二讀辯論。條例草案委員會主席郭榮亨議員就委員會報告向本會發言。郭榮亨議員。
Third-party funding of arbitration excludes the provision of arbitration funding directly or indirectly by lawyers and persons providing legal services. Hence, the Bills Committee requests the administration to explain the relevant policy considerations.
the bills committee supports the arbitration and mediation legislation third party funding bill, which seeks to amend the arbitration ordinance and the mediation ordinance to ensure that third party funding of arbitration and mediation is not prohibited by the common law doctrines of maintenance and champerty.
Bills committee generally supports the bill. In the course of scrutiny, the Bills committee has examined the meaning of third party funding of arbitration, meaning of funding agreement and third party funder, safeguards to be provided by the code and consequences of non compliance and application of the new Part 10A.
The administration has advised that lawyer funding of a party's participating in the arbitrations or litigation proceedings may occur through the use of fee arrangements under which a lawyer agrees to represent a party at a discount or for no fee, but with a successful
Administration has explained that it agreed to the Law Reforms Commission recommendation that it was in the public interest that lawyers should focus on their provision of professional services to their clients and should not place themselves in a conflict of interest position by engaging in the business of third party.
嗯。
The new Part Ten A.
律師的實務，acts for any party in relation to the arbitration.
And I commend the secretary for justice' work in this area in the past five years.
interests as a legal practitioner who does arbitration cases from time to time.
amendments to delete the new section 98G subsection 2 from and to add a new section 98NA to the new part of
98G subsection 2 from Hong Kong International Arbitration Centre, Hong Kong Bar Association and the Law Society of Hong Kong, as well as members of the public.
幾週後，行政局在中四月二零一七年引入一套委員會階段修訂，行政局確認參與者已諮詢過。
for arbitration in this jurisdiction, that is to say, whether lawyers can provide services in return for an agreed sum, conditional upon the winning of the case or sharing a portion of the award that the arbitration tribunal may award in due course.
most members of the bills committee, however, do not subscribe to the administration's views and considered unfair and overstringent to apply the exclusion slowly solely to third-party funding for arbitration provided by persons practising law or providing legal services in Hong Kong or else.
The Bills Committee has agreed that it would propose a committee stage amendment to delete the new Section 98G subsection 2. The Bills Committee also invited in late March 2017 views on the said committee stage amendment to be proposed by it to delete the new Section 98G.
行政已經考慮了法案委員會成員對新第98G節第2小節的意見，並為達到適當的平衡，確保合法的有關可能的利益衝突的擔憂得到充分處理，而提出委員會階段。
the bills committee notes that the proposed committee stage amendments operate to the effect that the common law doctrines of champerty and maintenance remain applicable to arbitration funding provided by a lawyer if such funding is provided to a party to an arbitration by a lawyer who, in the course of the
The bill's committee has examined all the proposed committee stage amendments from the administration and raised no objection thereto. The bill's committee will not propose any committee stage amendments to the bill. Madam President, next I would like to give my personal views on the bill. And first of all, I would like to declare my
Madam President, it is with pleasure and with delight to see two arbitration bills coming to Legco today, which seeks to improve the body of laws in relation to arbitration in Hong Kong, and is also a welcoming development for Hong Kong as a international legal and dispute resolution centre.
The most debated issue during the bill's committee deliberation is whether a lawyer is allowed to fund a arbitration case in which he or she is involved in. Of course, the real question is whether conditional fees or contingency fees are permitted.
周浩鼎議員。
In Hong Kong. Thank you.
Members of the legal profession understand and respect that approach. However,
The experience of other common law jurisdiction in this regard would be helpful.
仲裁嘅業務嚟講咧，或者喺呢方面嘅產業嘅推動咧，我相信都係會一定嘅幫助。
It must be urged that this question of conditional fee and contingency fee can no longer be.
我們理解行政局的立場，即係希望就應急費和條件費安排問題，謹慎處理，並採取逐步的措施。
國際法律和爭議解決中心，法律 profession 必須跟上其他司法管轄區的發展，因為他們在與來自其他司法管轄區的律師競爭，特別是在國際仲裁領域。
那經驗 tells us that as long as there are sufficient and adequate safeguards in place, for example, a requirement for minimum capital access by the relevant law firm in question, and appropriate measures to avoid conflict of interest, the interests of litigants can be protected.
left in the shelves and not be properly discussed in the Legislative Council, as one could see in many other jurisdiction, lawyers are allowed to be to engage in conditional and contingency fee arrangement, and it is making Hong Kong less and less competitive as a
Madam President, the members of the legal profession greatly welcome the passage of the arbitration bills today, and we hope to see further promotional efforts and further resources that will be put into the promotion of the arbitration and legal services.
啊，主席，對於咧呢一個嘅啊仲裁及調解法例第三方資助修訂嘅條例草案咧，啊，我係表示歡迎。啊，亦都坦白講咧，喺呢一個第三方資助仲裁嘅方案得到通過之後咧，我相信對於香港推動嗰個
保障翻仲裁雙方嘅。
咁呢個係我嘅一個第一點嘅建議啦。
方面咧，我都希望能夠密切咁監察，因為咧。
喺實施嘅期間咧，特別係頭三年期間咧，就繼續密切注視裡面嗰個嘅監察嘅情況。
誒，我哋嘅委員亦都多翻表達嘅意見咧，係可以容許執業嘅律師或者係執業嘅大律師咧，亦都係參與第三方資助嗰個嘅誒誒，參與佢嗰個業務嘅。
啊！主席喺度咧，我講少少關於對於呢條條例草案嘅一啲嘅簡單嘅意見。第一咧就係誒，我記得咧喺比較早期嘅時候，呢一個嘅條例草案嘅泛委員會嘅討論裏面咧，我自己都有提出過咧，就係話誒喺一個一般市民嘅角度咧，可能佢哋會諗。
嗰一樣嘢就係，如果容許第三方去資助一個仲裁嘅進行嘅時候，會唔會嗰個誒仲裁嘅過程裡面係變成由個出資者個第三方咧係掌握咗比較大嘅話語權，甚至乎會影響到仲裁雙方個作出決定嘅時候。
嘅情況會有一定嘅影響咧，咁咁呢個誒主席呢個問題咧，其實對於好多個普通市民嚟講咧，佢可能都會諗到有噉嘅情況。咁然而咧就誒，我慶幸咧亦都喺條例裡面咧，今次亦都講清楚咧，就係話對於呢個第三者嘅資助嘅安排。
排咧係必須要係按照九十八H條咧係要訂立一個書面協議，亦都講得好清楚咧，係佢嘅資助裡面嘅條款講得好清楚，亦唔係去啊主動去影響佢嗰個嘅仲裁裡面咧產生個嘅決定啊。我相信咧呢樣嘢咧係亦都有助於咧釐清。
呢一個方面嘅憂慮啊，呢個咧，我認為咧就係值得啊，我哋認為係啱嘅一件事情嚟嘅。咁但係亦都要提醒咧，就係對於啊將來嘅條例出台之後啦，亦都可以提醒翻公眾嘅權利，就係話咧，縱然第三方嘅誒對你呢個。
用財嘅案件嘅資助咧，亦都唔係話一定就構成佢會有一個話語權去決定你個案件裡面嗰個最後嘅誒取態嘅啊。中間嘅大家嘅嗰個第三方資助嘅嗰個要有嘅所有嘅條款咧，亦都要透過書面協議咧去做好做寫清楚出嚟，咁咪保。
第二點咧就係主席啊，而家咧我哋呢一個嘅條例咧，將來會採取嘅規管模式咧，都係一個輕力度嘅規管模式。咁呢種嘅模式咧，其實喺一啲其他嘅普通法嘅司法管轄區，亦都係用緊嘅。噉啊，對我嚟講咧，我認為咧，用採用首先試下採用輕力。
度嘅規管模式亦都係誒可以係接受，亦都合理嘅一個做法。咁咧就三年嘅嗰個嘅誒開展嘅期間咧，我希望咧當局咧都係密切注視嗰個實施嘅情況，特別係咧對於第三者誒出資去資助嘅佢哋呢方面嘅行為同埋操守嗰方。
誒，如果係誒唔係情況出現得好壞，或者係自從有咗呢樣嘢之後，有一啲不法嘅行為出現咗，或者違規嘅情況出現嘅話咧，啊，我認為咧呢種輕力度嘅啊規管嘅模式咧，誒將來咧都可以繼續嘅。咁不過咧，亦都希望當局咧係啊。
under Hong Kong law.
有冇其他議員想發言？
legal services, whether in Hong Kong or elsewhere.
如果冇，我現在請律政司司長答辯，之後辯論即告結束，司長。
方面嘅業務，亦都開開始繼續咧，係推動香港作為一個國際仲裁中心，去鞏固我哋呢方面嘅地位嘅。誒，主席，我緊止陳詞。
我將會在委員會階段提出修訂，於後續階段，CSAs已全部獲得法案委員會的贊同，並可簡要概述如下。
我亦感謝發展參與者在法律、仲裁、調解及相關專業領域的專業人士，對他們的寶貴意見及支持。
The bill will reflect in our legislation the latest developments in the dispute resolution sector, and further enhance Hong Kong's status as a leading centre for international legal and dispute resolution services in the Asia Pacific region.
The government has carefully considered the requests and the views of members. We take the view that a proper balance should be struck by ensuring that legitimate concerns over potential conflicts of interest are sufficiently addressed.
Some members of the Bills Committee have suggested to delete the proposed Section 98G bracket 2, so that the clarification to permit the provision of arbitration funding will also apply to all qualified lawyers and other legal services providers.
最後一點咧，就係主席啊！我哋喺法案委員會嘅誒過程、討論過程裏邊咧，其實都啊對於一點係有爭論過比較長嘅時間，就係咧我哋法律界啊誒執業嘅律師係或者執業嘅大律師係唔係能夠可以成為一個參與呢個第三方？
資助嘅業務啊，喺呢一度咧，誒可以話畀大家聽咧，喺法案委員會裏面咧的，而且確有個比較激烈嘅爭論啊。其實咧喺對於我哋法律界嘅行業嚟講咧，當然我哋亦都係比較傾向認為咧，啊對於參與第三方資助嘅呢個業務嚟講咧，其實法律界嘅執
業嘅律師或者係大律師嚟講咧，相信亦都係有掌握咗一定嘅經驗同埋佢哋嘅知識去誒誒做呢一方面嘅業務嘅。咁然而當然咧，要個平衡點咧，就係話千萬咧唔會引起任何嘅利益衝突。咁咧誒喺今次嘅政府嘅最後有一個嘅修正。
案決定出翻嚟咧，就係亦都聽咗好多我哋嘅委員嘅意見，就最後咧嘅修正案咧，都認為咧，只要係如果係律師咧喺仲裁嗰方面，佢唔係代表仲裁嘅任何一方行事嘅話咧，噉就佢去參與嗰個第三方資助而言咧，就應該係可以接受嘅啊，亦都唔。
唔會違反到嗰個所謂包攬訴訟嘅嗰個情況咁誒，但當然啦。如果係佢已經係代表緊訴訟嘅其中一方嘅話咧，當然不能夠讓佢再成為一個第三方資助者或者係參與呢個業務，因為咧恐防係會有呢個呢啲嘅衝突。但如果唔係呢個情況底下咧。
啊！喺呢度咧，政府亦都作咗一定嘅誒修正嚇。噉我哋啊，我個人嚟講咧，對於政府一個修正咧，亦都係表示一個歡迎。咁誒，最後咧就主席，我希望咧誒，透過今次嘅條例生效之後咧，能夠可以再進一步咧係促進香港嘅嗰個誒仲裁嘅嗰。
主席，首先，我會表達我們對丹尼斯·考克，即係法案委員會主席，關於《仲裁及調解條例》第三方撥款修訂法案2016，即係法案，以及所有其他委員會成員的辛勤工作，完成對法案的審查的感謝。
作為我指出，當引入這項法案到這個議會在本年1月，主要目的的法案是修訂仲裁條例第609號和調解條例第620號，以釐清第三方撥款，仲裁、調解和相關程序是允許。
The proposed amendments were formulated on the basis of the recommendations made in the report on third-party funding for arbitration, published by the Law Reform Commission of Hong Kong (the LRC) in October 2016, and the outcome of consultation with the Steering Committee on Mediation.
acting for parties in the arbitration.
party funding of mediation from that person.
修改，至調解，至何處調解條例適用。
so as to ensure that the latest developments in the dispute resolution community can be promptly and appropriately reflected in our legislation.
Hong Kong， and D the above disclosure requirements apply to a professional adviser. The home mediation communication is provided.
B. The disclosure must be for the purpose of having or seeking third-party funding for mediation or obtaining professional advice in this connection.
A person who intends to mediate a dispute, or is in the course of mediating a dispute, may disclose mediation communication for specified purposes.
by virtue of the new section 98A, lawyers who put themselves in such a conflict of interest situation will not be protected by the proposed Part 10A of the arbitration ordinance.
We now propose CSAs to the new Section 7A, for the purpose of the mitigation ordinance. The original proposed Section 98S will be substituted by a new Section 98S. The effect of the CSA is as follows.
Under the proposed section 98G, bracket two of the of the arbitration ordinance in clause three of the bill, third-party funding of arbitration does not include the provision of arbitration funding directly or indirectly by a person practising law or providing.
safeguards ought to be put in place to ensure that a lawyer should not be allowed to provide arbitration or mediation funding if the lawyer concerned acts for any party in relevant proceedings. Therefore, we now propose CSAs to, first of all, delete the proposed.
section ninety eight capital G two bracket two and secondly at a new section ninety eight capital N capital A so that the new third party funding regime under the proposed part ten capital A of the arbitration ordinance will not be applicable to lawyers.
在Putting forward the above proposal, we fully agree with the LLC that it would be in the public interest for lawyers to focus on their provision of provisional services to their clients, and that they should not place themselves in a conflict of interest position by engaging in the business of third-party funding.
Clause four of the bill proposed to add a new section seven capital A to the mediation ordinance. The new section seven capital A of the mediation ordinance extends, among others, the application of the new section ninety eight capital S of the arbitration ordinance, with the necessary.
Under this original proposal, despite the confidentiality requirements provided in Section 8, Capital 1 of the mediation ordinance, mediation communication referred to in that section may be disclosed by a party to mediation to a person for the purpose of having or seeking.
二零。
園中菜。
反對嘅請舉手。
and the amendments that I will move at the subsequent committee stage. Thank you, President.
我認為議題獲得在席議員以過半數贊成，我宣佈議案獲得通過。
《法例第三者資助修訂條例草案》，本會現在成為全體委員會就條例。
我現在向各位提出嘅代決議題係《二零一六年仲裁及調解法例第三者資助修訂條例草案》予以議讀，贊成嘅請舉手。
C. With the leave of the relevant court or tribunal, a fund party and a third party funder may disclose mediation communication for the purpose of protecting, pursuing or enforcing rights or interests in relation to the third party funding of mediation in legal proceedings in or outside.
The Department of Justice has been making every effort to consolidate the status of Hong Kong as a leading centre for international legal and dispute resolution services in the Asia-Pacific region. We will consider improvements to the provisions of the Arbitration Ordinance and the Mediation Ordinance as and when appropriate.
作為我提到在引入法案到議會時，第三方仲裁和其他爭議解決程序的資金已經變得越來越普遍，在許多司法管轄區，包括澳大利亞、英格蘭和威爾斯、各個歐洲國家和美國。
We believe that the passage of the bill and the CSA would enable Hong Kong's dispute resolution regime to stay at the forefront among major dispute resolution and financial centres around the world. With these remarks, President, I urge members to support the bill.